<tei:TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:j="http://jewishliturgy.org/ns/jlptei/2" xml:lang="en">
  <tei:teiHeader>
    <tei:fileDesc>
      <tei:titleStmt>
        <tei:title type="main" xml:lang="en">Haggai</tei:title>
        <tei:title type="alt" xml:lang="he">חגי</tei:title>
        <tei:respStmt>
          <tei:resp key="trc">Transcribed by</tei:resp>
          <tei:name ref="urn:x-opensiddur:contributor:en.wikisource.org/EncycloPetey">EncycloPetey (English Wikisource contributor)</tei:name>
        </tei:respStmt>
      </tei:titleStmt>
      <tei:publicationStmt>
        <tei:distributor>
          <tei:ref target="http://opensiddur.org">Open Siddur Project</tei:ref>
        </tei:distributor>
        <tei:idno type="urn">urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:tanakh@jps1917</tei:idno>
        <tei:availability status="free">
          <tei:licence target="http://www.creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication 1.0</tei:licence>
        </tei:availability>
      </tei:publicationStmt>
      <tei:sourceDesc>
        <tei:bibl>
          <tei:title>Bible (Jewish Publication Society 1917)</tei:title>
          <tei:distributor>
            <tei:ref target="https://en.wikisource.org">Wikisource</tei:ref>
          </tei:distributor>
          <tei:idno type="url">https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Bible_(Jewish_Publication_Society_1917)</tei:idno>
          <tei:date>2025-07-27</tei:date>
        </tei:bibl>
        <tei:bibl>
          <tei:title type="main">The Holy Scriptures</tei:title>
          <tei:title type="sub">According to the Masoretic Text: A New Translation With The Aid of Previous Versions And With Constant Consultation of Jewish Authorities</tei:title>
          <tei:title xml:lang="he" type="alt">תורה נביאים וכתובים</tei:title>
          <tei:edition>Third Impression, August 1919</tei:edition>
          <tei:publisher>Jewish Publication Society of America</tei:publisher>
          <tei:pubPlace>Philadelphia</tei:pubPlace>
          <tei:date>1917</tei:date>
          <tei:note>Lakeside Press, Chicago</tei:note>
        </tei:bibl>
      </tei:sourceDesc>
    </tei:fileDesc>
  </tei:teiHeader>
  <tei:text>
    <tei:body xmlns:j="http://jewishliturgy.org/ns/jlptei/2" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <tei:div type="book" n="haggai" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai">
        <tei:pb n="757"/>
        <tei:head><tei:foreign xml:lang="he">חגי</tei:foreign><tei:lb/>
HAGGAI</tei:head>
        <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="chapter" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1"/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/1"/><tei:hi rend="small-caps">In</tei:hi> the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, came the word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> by Haggai the prophet unto Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/2"/>'Thus speaketh the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts, saying: This people say: The time is not come, the time that the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord's</tei:hi> house should be built.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="3" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/3"/>Then came the word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> by Haggai the prophet, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="4" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/4"/>'Is it a time for you yourselves to dwell in your ceiled houses, while this house lieth waste? <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="5" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/5"/>Now therefore thus saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts:</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:lb/>Consider your ways. 
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="6" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/6"/>Ye have sown much, and brought in little,
<tei:lb/>Ye eat, but ye have not enough,
<tei:lb/>Ye drink, but ye are not filled with drink,
<tei:lb/>Ye clothe you, but there is none warm;
<tei:lb/>And he that earneth wages earneth wages
<tei:lb/>For a bag with holes.</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="7" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/7"/>Thus saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts. Consider your ways. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="8" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/8"/>Go up to the hill-country, and bring wood, and build the house; and I will take pleasure in it, and I will be glorified, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="9" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/9"/>Ye looked for much, and, lo, it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did blow upon it. Why? saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts. Because of My house that lieth waste, while ye run every man for, his own house. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="10" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/10"/>Therefore over you the heaven hath kept back, so that there is no dew, and the earth hath kept back her produce. house. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="11" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/11"/>And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the mountains, and upon the corn, and upon the wine, and upon the oil, and upon that which the ground bringeth forth, and upon men, and upon cattle, and upon all the labour of the hands.'</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="12" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/12"/>Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, hearkened unto the voice of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> their God, and unto the words of Haggai the prophet, as the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> their God had sent him; and the people did fear before the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>. house. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="13" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/13"/>Then spoke Haggai the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord's</tei:hi> messenger in the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord's</tei:hi> message unto the people, saying: 'I am with you, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>.' house. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="14" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/14"/>And the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and did work in the house of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts, their God, house. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="15" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/1/15"/>in the four and twentieth day of the month, in the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king.</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="chapter" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2"/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/1"/>In the seventh month, in the one and twentieth day of the month, came the word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> by Haggai the prophet, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/2"/>'Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="3" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/3"/>Who is left among you that saw this house in its former glory? and how do <tei:pb n="758"/>
ye see it now? is not such a one as nothing in your eyes? <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="4" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/4"/>Yet now be strong, Zerubbabel, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>; and be strong, O Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest; and be strong, all ye people of the land, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, and work; for I am with you, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="5" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/5"/>The word that I covenanted with you when ye came out of Egypt have I established, and My spirit abideth among you; fear ye not. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="6" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/6"/>For thus saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts. Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the heavens, and the earth, and the sea, and the dry land; <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="7" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/7"/>and I will shake all nations, and the choicest things of all nations shall come, and I will fill this house with glory, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="8" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/8"/>Mine is the silver, and Mine the gold, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="9" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/9"/>The glory of this latter house shall be greater than that of the former, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts; and in this place will I give peace, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts.'</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="10" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/10"/>In the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, in the second year of Darius, came the word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> by Haggai the prophet, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="11" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/11"/>'Thus saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts: Ask now the priests for instruction, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="12" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/12"/>If one bear hallowed flesh in the skirt of his garment, and with his skirt do touch bread, or pottage, or wine, or oil, or any food, shall it become holy?' And the priests answered and said: 'No.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="13" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/13"/>Then said Haggai: 'If one that is unclean by a dead body touch any of these, shall it be unclean?' And the priests answered and said: 'It shall be unclean.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="14" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/14"/>Then answered Haggai and said: 'So is this people, and so is this nation before Me, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>; and so is every work of their hands; and that which they offer there is unclean. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="15" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/15"/>And now, I pray you, consider from this day and forward—before a stone was kid upon a stone in the temple of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="16" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/16"/>through all that time, when one came to a heap of twenty measures, there were but ten; when one came to the winevat to draw out fifty press-measures, there were but twenty; <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="17" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/17"/>I smote you with blasting and with mildew and with hail in all the work of your hands; yet ye turned not to Me, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>—<tei:milestone unit="verse" n="18" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/18"/>consider, I pray you, from this day and forward, from the four and twentieth day of the ninth month, even from the day that the foundation of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord's</tei:hi> temple was laid, consider it; <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="19" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/19"/>is the seed yet in the barn? yea, the vine, and the fig-tree, and the pomegranate, and the olive-tree hath not brought forth from this day will I bless you.'</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="20" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/20"/>And the word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> came the second time unto Haggai in the four and twentieth day of the month, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="21" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/21"/>'Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying: I will shake the heavens and the earth; <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="22" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/22"/>and I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms, and I will destroy the strength of the kingdoms of the nations; and I will overthrow the chariots, and those that ride in them; and the horses and their riders shall come down, every one by the sword of his brother. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="23" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:haggai/2/23"/>In that day, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts, will I take thee, Zerubbabel, My servant, the son of Shealtiel, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, and will make thee as a signet; for I have chosen thee, saith the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> of hosts.'
</tei:p>
      </tei:div>
    </tei:body>
  </tei:text>
</tei:TEI>