<tei:TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:j="http://jewishliturgy.org/ns/jlptei/2" xml:lang="en">
  <tei:teiHeader>
    <tei:fileDesc>
      <tei:titleStmt>
        <tei:title type="main" xml:lang="en">Jonah</tei:title>
        <tei:title type="alt" xml:lang="he">יונה</tei:title>
        <tei:respStmt>
          <tei:resp key="trc">Transcribed by</tei:resp>
          <tei:name ref="urn:x-opensiddur:contributor:en.wikisource.org/EncycloPetey">EncycloPetey (English Wikisource contributor)</tei:name>
        </tei:respStmt>
      </tei:titleStmt>
      <tei:publicationStmt>
        <tei:distributor>
          <tei:ref target="http://opensiddur.org">Open Siddur Project</tei:ref>
        </tei:distributor>
        <tei:idno type="urn">urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:tanakh@jps1917</tei:idno>
        <tei:availability status="free">
          <tei:licence target="http://www.creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication 1.0</tei:licence>
        </tei:availability>
      </tei:publicationStmt>
      <tei:sourceDesc>
        <tei:bibl>
          <tei:title>Bible (Jewish Publication Society 1917)</tei:title>
          <tei:distributor>
            <tei:ref target="https://en.wikisource.org">Wikisource</tei:ref>
          </tei:distributor>
          <tei:idno type="url">https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Bible_(Jewish_Publication_Society_1917)</tei:idno>
          <tei:date>2025-07-27</tei:date>
        </tei:bibl>
        <tei:bibl>
          <tei:title type="main">The Holy Scriptures</tei:title>
          <tei:title type="sub">According to the Masoretic Text: A New Translation With The Aid of Previous Versions And With Constant Consultation of Jewish Authorities</tei:title>
          <tei:title xml:lang="he" type="alt">תורה נביאים וכתובים</tei:title>
          <tei:edition>Third Impression, August 1919</tei:edition>
          <tei:publisher>Jewish Publication Society of America</tei:publisher>
          <tei:pubPlace>Philadelphia</tei:pubPlace>
          <tei:date>1917</tei:date>
          <tei:note>Lakeside Press, Chicago</tei:note>
        </tei:bibl>
      </tei:sourceDesc>
    </tei:fileDesc>
  </tei:teiHeader>
  <tei:text>
    <tei:body xmlns:j="http://jewishliturgy.org/ns/jlptei/2" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <tei:div type="book" n="jonah" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah">
        <tei:pb n="736"/>
        <tei:div type="book" n="jonah_1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah_1">
          <tei:head><tei:foreign xml:lang="he">יונה</tei:foreign><tei:lb/>
JONAH</tei:head>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="chapter" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1"/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/1"/><tei:hi rend="small-caps">Now</tei:hi> the word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> came unto Jonah the son of Amittai, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/2"/>'Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and proclaim against it; For their wickedness is come up before Me.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="3" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/3"/>But Jonah rose up to flee unto Tarshish from the presence of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>; and he went down to Joppa, and found a ship going to Tarshish; so he paid the fare thereof, and went down into it, to go with them unto Tarshish, from the presence of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>.</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="4" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/4"/>But the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> hurled a great wind into the sea, and there was a mighty tempest in the sea, so that the ship was like to be broken. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="5" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/5"/>And the mariners were afraid, and cried every man unto his god; and they cast forth the wares that were in the ship into the sea, to lighten it unto them. But Jonah was gone down into the innermost parts of the ship; and he lay, and was fast asleep. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="6" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/6"/>So the shipmaster came to him, and said unto him: 'What meanest thou that thou sleepest? arise, call upon thy God, if so be that God will think upon us, that we perish not.'</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="7" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/7"/>And they said every one to his fellow: 'Come, and let us cast lots, that we may know for whose cause this evil is upon us.' So they cast lots, and the lot fell upon Jonah. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="8" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/8"/>Then said they unto him: 'Tell us, we pray thee, for whose cause this evil is upon us: what is thine occupation? and whence comest thou? what is thy country? and of what people art thou? <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="9" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/9"/>And he said unto them:  <tei:pb n="737"/>
'I am a Hebrew; and I fear the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, the God of heaven, who hath made the sea and the dry land.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="10" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/10"/>Then were the men exceedingly afraid, and said unto him: 'What is this that thou hast done?' For the men knew that he fled from the presence of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, because he had told them.</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="11" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/11"/>Then said they unto him: 'What shall we do unto thee, that the sea may be calm unto us?' for the sea grew more and more tempestuous. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="12" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/12"/>And he said unto them: 'Take me up, and cast me forth into the sea; so shall the sea be calm unto you; for I know that for my sake this great tempest is upon you.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="13" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/13"/>Nevertheless the men rowed hard to bring it to the land; but they could not; for the sea grew more and more tempestuous against them. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="14" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/14"/>Wherefore they cried unto the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, and said: 'We beseech Thee, O <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, we beseech Thee, let us not perish for this man's life, and lay not upon us innocent blood; for Thou, O <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, hast done as it pleased Thee.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="15" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/15"/>So they took up Jonah, and cast him forth into the sea; and the sea ceased from its raging. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="16" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/16"/>Then the men feared the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> exceedingly; and they offered a sacrifice unto the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, and made vows.</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="chapter" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2"/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/1"/>And the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah; and Jonah was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/2"/>Then Jonah prayed unto the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> his God out of the fish's belly. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="3" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/3"/>And he said:</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:lb/>I called out of mine affliction
<tei:lb/>Unto the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, and He answered me;
<tei:lb/>Out of the belly of the nether-world cried I,
<tei:lb/>And Thou heardest my voice.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="4" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/4"/>For thou didst cast me into the depth,
<tei:lb/>In the heart of the seas,
<tei:lb/>And the flood was round about me;
<tei:lb/>All Thy waves and Thy billows
<tei:lb/>Passed over me.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="5" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/5"/>And I said: 'I am cast out
<tei:lb/>From before Thine eyes';
<tei:lb/>Yet I will look again
<tei:lb/>Toward Thy holy temple.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="6" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/6"/>The waters compassed me about, even to the soul;
<tei:lb/>The deep was round about me;
<tei:lb/>The weeds were wrapped about my head.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="7" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/7"/>I went down to the bottoms of the mountains;
<tei:lb/>The earth with her bars closed upon me for ever;
<tei:lb/>Yet hast Thou brought up my life from the pit,
<tei:lb/>O <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> my God.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="8" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/8"/>When my soul fainted within me,
<tei:lb/>I remembered the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>;
<tei:lb/>And my prayer came in unto Thee,
<tei:lb/>Into Thy holy temple.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="9" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/9"/>They that regard lying vanities
<tei:lb/>Forsake their own mercy.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="10" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/10"/>But I will sacrifice unto Thee
<tei:lb/>With the voice of thanksgiving;
<tei:lb/>That which I have vowed I will pay.
<tei:lb/>Salvation is of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>.</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="11" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/2/11"/>And the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> spoke unto the fish, and it vomited out Jonah upon the dry land.</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="chapter" n="3" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3"/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/1"/>And the word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> came unto Jonah the second time, saying: <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/2"/>'Arise, go unto Nineveh, that great city, and make unto it the proclamation that I bid thee.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="3" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/3"/>So Jonah arose, and went unto Nineveh, according to the word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>. Now Nineveh was an exceeding great city, of three days' journey. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="4" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/4"/>And Jonah began to enter into the city a day's journey, and he proclaimed, and said: 'Yet forty days, and Nineveh shall be overthrown.'</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="5" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/5"/>And the people of Nineveh believed God; and they proclaimed a <tei:pb n="738"/>
fast, and put on sackcloth, from the 
greatest of them even to the least of 
them. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="6" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/6"/>And the tidings reached the 
king of Nineveh, and he arose from 
his throne, and laid his robe from him, 
and covered him with sackcloth, and sat in ashes. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="7" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/7"/>And he caused it to be proclaimed and published through Nineveh by the decree of the king and his nobles, saying: 'Let neither man nor beast, herd nor flock, taste any thing; let them not feed, nor drink water; <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="8" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/8"/>but let them be covered with sackcloth, both man and beast, and let them cry mightily unto God; yea, let them turn every one from his evil way, and from the violence that is in their hands. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="9" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/9"/>Who knoweth whether God will not turn and repent, and turn away from His fierce anger, that we perish not?'</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="10" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/3/10"/>And God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way; and God repented of the evil, which He said He would do unto them; and He did it not. {{float left|{{dropinitial|4}}}}<tei:milestone unit="chapter" n="4" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4"/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/1"/>But it displeased Jonah exceedingly, and he was angry. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/2"/>And he prayed unto the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, and said: 'I pray Thee, O <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, was not this my saying, when I was yet in mine own country? Therefore I fled beforehand unto Tarshish; for I knew that Thou art a gracious God, and compassionate, long-suffering, and abundant in mercy, and repentest Thee of the evil. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="3" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/3"/>Therefore now, O <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi>, take, I beseech Thee, my life from me; for it is better for me to die than to live.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="4" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/4"/>And the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> said: 'Art thou greatly angry?'</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="5" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/5"/>Then Jonah went out of the city, and sat on the east side of the city, and there made him a booth, and sat under it in the shadow, till he might see what would become of the city. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="6" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/6"/>And the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> God prepared a gourd, and made it to come up over Jonah, that it might be a shadow over his head, to deliver him from his evil. So Jonah was exceeding glad because of the gourd. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="7" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/7"/>But God prepared a worm when the morning rose the next day, and it smote the gourd, that it withered. <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="8" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/8"/>And it came to pass, when the sun arose, that God prepared a vehement east wind; and the sun beat upon the head of Jonah, that he fainted, and requested for himself that he might die, and said: 'It is better for me to die than to live.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="9" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/9"/>And God said to Jonah 'Art thou greatly angry for the gourd?' And he said: 'I am greatly angry, even unto death.' <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="10" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/10"/>And the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> said: 'Thou hast had pity on the gourd, for which thou hast not laboured, neither madest it grow, which came up in a night, and perished in a night; <tei:milestone unit="verse" n="11" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/4/11"/>and should not I have pity on Nineveh, that great city, wherein are more than sixscore thousand persons that cannot discern Between their right hand and their left hand, and also much cattle?' 
 <tei:pb n="739"/>
</tei:p>
        </tei:div>
        <tei:div type="book" n="jonah_2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah_2">
          <tei:head><tei:foreign xml:lang="he">מיכה</tei:foreign><tei:lb/>
MICAH</tei:head>
          <tei:p><tei:milestone unit="chapter" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1"/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="1" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/1"/><tei:hi rend="small-caps">The</tei:hi> word of the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> that came to Micah the Morashtite in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, which he saw concerning Samaria and Jerusalem.</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="2" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/2"/>Hear, ye peoples, all of you,
<tei:lb/>Hearken, O earth, and all that therein is;
<tei:lb/>And let the Lord <tei:hi rend="small-caps">God</tei:hi> be witness against you,
<tei:lb/>The Lord from His holy temple.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="3" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/3"/>For, behold, the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> cometh forth out of His place,
<tei:lb/>And will come down, and tread upon the high places of the earth.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="4" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/4"/>And the mountains shall be molten under Him,
<tei:lb/>And the valleys shall be cleft,
<tei:lb/>As wax before the fire,
<tei:lb/>As waters that are poured down a steep place.
</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="5" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/5"/>For the transgression of Jacob is all this,
<tei:lb/>And for the sins of the house of Israel.
<tei:lb/>What is the transgression of Jacob? is it not Samaria?
<tei:lb/>And what are the high places of Judah? are they not Jerusalem?
</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="6" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/6"/>Therefore I will make Samaria a heap in the field,
<tei:lb/>A place for the planting of vineyards;
<tei:lb/>And I will pour down the stones thereof into the valley,
<tei:lb/>And I will uncover the foundations thereof.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="7" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/7"/>And all her graven images shall be beaten to pieces,
<tei:lb/>And all her hires shall be burned with fire,
<tei:lb/>And all her idols will I lay desolate;
<tei:lb/>For of the hire of a harlot hath she gathered them,
<tei:lb/>And unto the hire of a harlot shall they return.
</tei:p>
          <tei:p><tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="8" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/8"/>For this will I wail and howl,
<tei:lb/>I will go stripped and naked;
<tei:lb/>I will make a wailing like the jackals,
<tei:lb/>And a mourning like the ostriches.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="9" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/9"/>For her wound is incurable;
<tei:lb/>For it is come even unto Judah;
<tei:lb/>It reacheth unto the gate of my people, even to Jerusalem.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="10" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/10"/>Tell it not in Gath,
<tei:lb/>Weep not at all;
<tei:lb/>At Beth-le-aphrah roll thyself in the dust.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="11" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/11"/>Pass ye away, O inhabitant of Shaphir, in nakedness and shame;
<tei:lb/>The inhabitant of Zaanan is not come forth;
<tei:lb/>The wailing of Beth-ezel shall take from you the standing-place thereof.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="12" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/12"/>For the inhabitant of Maroth waiteth anxiously for good;
<tei:lb/>Because evil is come down from the <tei:hi rend="small-caps">Lord</tei:hi> unto the gate of Jerusalem.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="13" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/13"/>Bind the chariots to the swift steeds, O inhabitant of Lachish;
<tei:lb/>She was the beginning of sin to the daughter of Zion;
<tei:lb/>For the transgressions of Israel are found in thee.
<tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="verse" n="14" corresp="urn:x-opensiddur:text:bible:jonah/1/14"/>Therefore shalt thou give a parting gift to Moresheth-gath;</tei:p>
        </tei:div>
      </tei:div>
    </tei:body>
  </tei:text>
</tei:TEI>